Guide to the Carl Spielvogel Papers, 1946-2014 and undated RL.10185
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Carl Spielvogel papers
1946-2014 and undated
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Spielvogel, Carl.
RL.10185
12 Linear Feet
Advertising executive at several U.S. agencies, including McCann-Erickson, Backer Spielvogel Bates, Interpublic Group, and Saatchi & Saatchi. Served as U.S. Ambassador to Slovakia during the Clinton Administration.
Related Materials
Related materials may be found in the following Hartman Center collections:
Bates Worldwide Inc. Records
Collection Overview
Collection spans 1946-2014 and contains correspondence, photographs, scrapbooks, printed materials, memorabilia, audiovisual materials and other items pertaining to Spielvogel's career in advertising as well as his public service and community activities. Advertising agencies represented include Backer Spielvogel Bates, Interpublic and Saatchi & Saatchi. Acquired as part of the John W. Hartman Center for Sales, Advertising & Marketing History.
Arrangement
Arranged into eight series: Carl and Barbalee Diamondstien Spielvogel Files; Personal Files; Photographs; Printed Material; Scrapbooks; Large Format Materials; Artifacts and Memorabilia; and Audiovisual Materials. Original folder titles have been preserved where possible.
Historical note
Biographical timeline
1928 Dec. 27 Born, New York, N.Y.
1950-1960 Reporter and Columnist, New York Times
1952 B.A., Business Administration, Baruch College, CUNY
1951-1955 Military service, U.S. Army, U.S. Air Force Reserve
1960 Joins McCann-Erickson, Public Relations Dept.
1969 Director, Group Vice President, McCann-Erickson
1970 Director, Interpublic Group of Companies; named Vice Chairman in 1974
1971 General Manager and Chairman of Executive Committee, McCann-Erickson
1977 Chairman, Mayor's (Abraham Beame) Committee in the Public Interest
1982 Marketer of the Year, New York Chapter of the American Marketing Association
1987-1994 Chairman, Backer Spielvogel Bates
1987 Crain's New York Business "Outstanding Executive"
1989 Chairman, New York State Democratic National Committee Dinner
1990 Distinguished Alumnus Award, Baruch College Board of Trustees, Executive Committee, Asia Society
1991 Chairman, Mayor's (David Dinkins) Committee for Public Private Partnership Finance Committee, Democratic National Committee
1992 Carl Spielvogel Lecture Series on Global Marketing Communications, Baruch College International Business Committee of the New York Partnership
1993 American Chairman, New York-Japan Festival
1994-1997 Chairman, CEO and Director, United Auto Group
1995 U.S. Broadcasting Board of Governors (Voice of America, Voice of Europe, Voice of Asia, Radio Marti, Worldnet)
1997 International Advisory Board, The Financial Times
1998 Fellow, Center for Business and Government, Kennedy School of Government, Harvard University
1999 H.E.L.P. Humanitarian Award
2001 Ambassador to Slovakia
1984 Honorary LLD, Baruch College Trustee, Metropolitan Museum of Art
Also: Board of Trustees of Metropolitan Museum of Art, Lincoln Center, New York Philharmonic, Mt. Sinai Hospital, Tennis Hall of Fame, Bennington College, New York State Council of the Humanities, Hasbro, Inc., Adjunct Professor of the Graduate School of Baruch College, Businessman in Residence at Fuqua Graduate School of Business at Duke University
Provenance
The Carl Spielvogel Papers were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a gift in 2012-2014
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
However, original audiovisual materials are closed to researchers until use copies can be produced.
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48-hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library to use this collection.
Advertising; Digital audio formats; Advertising -- United States -- History; Advertising -- United States; Scrapbooks; Photographs; Advertising executives; Advertising executives -- United States; Advertising agencies -- United States; Advertising agencies -- United States -- History; Advertising agencies; Advertising agencies -- History; Audiocassettes; Saatchi & Saatchi; Interpublic Group of Companies; Backer Spielvogel Bates (Firm)
- Carl and Barbalee Diamonstein-Spielvogel, 1986-2013 and undated; 1
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1986-2013 and undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1995 and undated (Box 1)
- Personal Files, 1946-2013 and undated; 2
  - Advertising Club of New York, Benevolent Dictators souvenir program, 1984 (Box 2)
  - Al Kamen articles, 1999-2000 and undated (Box 2)
  - Ambassadorship--Correspondence, 1999-2013 (Box 2)
  - Ambassadorship--Meetings and programs, 1999-2006 and undated (Box 2)
  - Art/Museums, 2001-2013 and undated (Box 2)
  - Articles, 1946-1989; 6 folders (Box 2)
  - Articles, 1990-2013; 2 folders (Box 3)
  - Asia tours, 1989-1990 (Box 3)
  - Backer Spielvogel Bates, 1980-2000 and undated; 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Baruch College CUNY (Diploma, lecture series letter from Mayor David Dinkins), 1952-2010 (Box 3)
  - Baruch College--Colin Powell Fellowship, 2003-2004 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence and miscellaneous, 1969-2013; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - CV and work history, 1971 and undated (Box 4)
  - Interpublic Group, 1968-1979; 2 folders (Box 4)
  - Invitations, 1976-2013 and undated (Box 4)
  - Martin Mayer, The Story of Ted Bates and Company, manuscript, 1965 (Box 4)
  - Meeting notes and business cards, 1995-2013 and undated (Box 4)
  - Personal history, 1953-2013 and undated (Box 5)
  - Pukyong National University, 2012 and undated (Box 5)
  - Saatchi & Saatchi, 1986 (Box 5)
  - So-Long Oogle (song/poem), undated (Box 5)
  - Speeches, 1979-2012 and undated; 2 folders (Box 5)
  - United Auto Group, 1994-1997 (Box 5)
- Photographs, 1956-2013 and undated; 3
  - 60th birthday party, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Ambassador meeting, undated (Box 5)
  - Anti-Defamation League, 1970 (Box 5)
  - Asia Society, Kitty Carlyl (sic, Carlisle?), 1995 (Box 5)
  - Award acceptance, undated (Box 5)
  - Award ceremony for Gene Jurkowski, 1988 (Box 5)
  - Award ceremony for Herbert M. Baum, undated (Box 5)
  - Award dinner, New York, undated (Box 5)
  - Award event, undated (Box 5)
  - Backer Spielvogel Bates, 1988-1990 and undated; 4 folders (Box 5)
  - Backer Spielvogel Bates, 1990; 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Business trip to Japan, 1979-1990 and undated (Box 6)
  - Community service award, undated (Box 6)
  - Cookout, undated (Box 6)
  - Council of Senior Centers, undated (Box 6)
  - Event at Metropolitan Museum of Art, undated (Box 6)
  - Family, 1975-1988 and undated (Box 6)
  - Fisher Award, undated (Box 6)
  - From Japan, undated (Box 6)
  - Graduation/Alumni event, undated, 11 folders (Box 6)
  - Group photographs, 1958-1996 and undated; 11 folders (Box 6)
  - International meeting, undated (Box 6)
  - J&B Scotch, undated (Box 6)
  - Meeting in Colombia, undated (Box 6)
  - Meeting in Slovakia, undated (Box 6)
  - Miller Brewing, undated (Box 6)
  - Miscellaneous, 1956-1998 and undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - New Zealand/Australia, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Obama campaign event, 2008 (Box 7)
  - Office in Slovakia, undated (Box 7)
  - Personal, 1981-1996 and undated; 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Photographs with Bill Clinton, undated (Box 7)
  - Photographs with governors, 2013 and undated (Box 7)
  - Portraits, 1976-1996 and undated; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Public events, undated, 4 folders (Box 7)
  - Pukyong National University, undated (Box 7)
  - Russia, 1989-1990 (Box 7)
  - Six Principles and Global Scan press conference, 1989 and undated (Box 7)
  - Slovakia, 2000 and undated (Box 7)
  - Thanksgiving, 1991 (Box 7)
  - Tennis, undated (Box 7)
  - Trip to China, 1979 (Box 7)
  - UJA Federation dinner, 1973-1977; 2 folders (Box 7)
  - Vacation, 1995-1996 (Box 7)
  - With Koch, Dinkins, 1988-1990 and undated (Box 7)
  - Worldwide management meeting (BSB), 1988 (Box 8)
  - Yacht party, undated (Box 8)
  - Miscellaneous negatives, 1979 and undated; 6 folders (Box 8)
  - Damaged photographs [Closed] (Box 9)
- Printed Material, 1959-2013; 4
  - Pop Culture vs. Real Culture (U.S. Dept. of State publication), 2013 (Box 10)
  - The Initiator (McCann-Erickson letters from the President), 1959-1961 (Box 10)
  - The Management of the Marketing Function (Clarence E. Eldridge essays published by the Association of National Advertisers), 1966 (Box 10)
- Scrapbooks, 1956-1988; 5
  - Bound scrapbook, 1956-1957 (Box 11)
  - Personal history, 1958-1988; 15 folders (Box 12)
- Large Format Materials, 1953-2008 and undated; 6
  - Article, Wedding Present for Spielvogel, undated (Box 13)
  - Articles, 1982-1996 (Box 13)
  - Backer Spielvogel Bates, Largest Small Agency in the World brochure, undated (Box 13)
  - Photographs, undated (Box 13)
  - Saatchi & Saatchi, 1986 (Box 13)
  - Advertising Age (including advertisement featuring Spielvogel), 1984-2005 (Box 14)
  - Ambassadorship appointment, 2000 (Box 14)
  - Overseas Press Club, 2008 (Box 14)
  - Photograph--Softball game, undated (Box 14)
  - Photograph featuring Bob Ludwig, Bob Lenz, Steve Leff, Bob Holmes, Bill Backer, 1986 (Box 14)
  - Saatchi Buys Backer & Spielvogel, 1986 (Box 14)
  - United Auto Group, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Appointment to Broadcasting Board of Governors, 1997 (Box 15)
  - Award--Signed painting at end of Ambassadorship, undated (Box 15)
  - Personal history, 1953-1987; 4 folders (Box 15)
  - Photograph--Museum of Modern Art, 1992, 1997; 2 folders (Box 15)
- Artifacts and Memorabilia, 1952-2012 and undated; 7
  - American flag (U.S. Department of State box), undated (Box 16)
  - U.S. Department of State non-official diplomatic pouch, undated (Box 16)
  - Carl Spielvogel "action figure" doll, undated (Box 17)
  - Figurine--Indiana National Guard, undated (Box 18)
  - Figurine--Indiana-Slovakia State Partnership Program, undated (Box 18)
  - Pen holder, Duke University Fuqua School of Business, undated (Box 18)
  - Tiffany clock, undated (Box 18)
  - Townsend Harris Medal, Notable Achievement Alumni, College of the City of New York, undated (Box 18)
  - Barnard Baruch Award of Achievement, City College Alumni Society, 1972 (Box 19)
  - Baruch College/Baruch College Fund award, 1990 (Box 19)
  - Global Youth Leadership Day, 2012 (Box 19)
  - Mounted article, Spielvogel Advances at Interpublic, 1974 (Box 19)
  - Mounted article, Mission Impossible Reform Team Works to Revive Slovakia, 2001 (Box 20)
  - Plaque, United Jewish Appeal, 1976 (Box 20)
  - Mounted article, A Small Ad Agency That's No Small Beer, 1981 (Box 21)
  - Plaque, Anti-Defamation League, 1972 (Box 22)
  - Mounted article, Printing News, 1977 (Box 22)
  - Mounted article, Miller Changes Agencies, 1979 (Box 23)
  - Mounted article, Advance of Young Birds at Interpublic, 1977 (Box 23)
  - Plaque--Alumni Association, CCNY, Alumnus of the Year, 1988 (Box 23)
  - Yearbook, Lexicon, Baruch College, 1952 (Box 23)
  - American Academy of Achievement, Golden Plate award, 1973 (Box 24)
- Audiovisual Materials, 1988-2013 and undated; 8
  - CNN Pinnacle Profiles, Carl Spielvogel, VHS., 1990 Nov. 17 (Box 25, Video-cassette RL10185-VHS-0001)
  - RL10185-VHS-0002. Baruch College: The Legacy, undated. VHS. (Box 25)
  - RL10185-VHS-0003. Lou Dobbs promo to Carl Spielvogel Interview, Moneyline/CNN, VHS., 1992 Dec. 3 (Box 25)
  - RL10185-VHS-0004. Baruch College Distinguished Alumni Dinner, VHS., 1990 June 18 (Box 25)
  - RL10185-VHS-0005. Carl Spielvogel, undated. VHS. (Box 25)
  - RL10185-VHS-0006. Carl Spielvogel's Visit to Malaysia, VHS., 1989 Sept (Box 25)
  - RL10185-3/4-0001. Video Monitoring Service, Carl Spielvogel, Evening News, Financial News Network, 3/4 inch video., 1988 Dec. 12 (Box 25)
  - RL10185-3/4-0002. Duck Soup Video, Morty's Miller Lite, Lite Brigade, Sel Pix and Trk Outs, 3/4 inch video., 1988 Oct. 26 (Box 25)
  - RL10185-3/4-0003. Cnn Interview with Carl Spielvogel, undated. 3/4 inch video. (Box 25)
  - RL10185-3/4-0004. Baruch College, C.S. Lecture Series Featuring Ted Turner, 3/4 inch video., 1992 Sept. 24 (Box 25)
  - RL10185-3/4-0005. Baruch College 1990 Distinquished Alumnus Tribute Dinner, 3/4 inch video., 1990 June 18 (Box 25)
  - RL10185-3/4-0006. Miller Lite flub reel, undated. 3/4 inch video. (Box 25)
  - RL10185-3/4-0007. Lou Dobbs promo to Carl Spielvogel Interview, Moneyline/CNN, 3/4 inch video., 1992 Dec. 3 (Box 25)
  - RL10185-3/4-0008. Video Memo, Carl Spielvogel, International Teamwork, 3/4 inch video., 1990 Spring (Box 25)
  - RL10185-3/4-0009. Backer & Spielvogel 6th Anniversary slide show, undated. 3/4 inch video. (Box 25)
  - RL10185-3/4-0010. Untitled, undated. 3/4 inch video. (Box 25)
  - RL10185-CD-0001. Book party, undated. CD-R. (Box 25)
  - RL10185-DVD-0001. BLSCI Symposium Keynote, copy 1, DVD., 2011 May 6 (Box 25)
  - RL10185-DVD-0002. BLSCI Symposium Keynote, copy 2, DVD., 2011 May 6 (Box 25)
  - RL10185-DVD-0003. Dedication Ceremony, US Memorial, UNMCK, DVD., 2013 July 28 (Box 25)
  - RL10185-DVD-0004. Ambassador Spielvogel Powerpoint presentation, DVD., 2011 May 6 (Box 25)
  - Oral history interview, 2013 June 19; 114 minutes